Guide to the Evelyn Simpson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Evelyn Simpson papers
1906-1963
OSB MSS 90
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.97
(28 boxes)
Correspondence and writings documenting aspects of the scholarly career of Evelyn Spearing Simpson, particularly her work on a complete edition of the Sermons of John Donne. Correspondents include her Donne collaborator George R. Potter and his wife Mabel; friend and fellow Donne scholar Helen Gardner; and Mary Holtby. Writings include research notes, drafts, typescripts and proofs of most volumes of the Sermons edition; and drafts and typescripts of scholarly articles on Donne's work.
Simpson, Evelyn Mary Spearing, 1885-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase by James M. Osborn from Evelyn Simpson and Mary Simpson Fleay, 1960-1964. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Percy Simpson Papers, OSB MSS 8.
EVELYN MARY SPEARING SIMPSON, 1885-1963
Evelyn Mary Spearing Simpson was born on September 2, 1885 and was educated at Perse School and Newnham College, Oxford. She taught at Bedford College and was a fellow at Newnham, leaving to join the V.A.D. (Voluntary Aid Detachment) as a nurse in France during World War I. At the end of the war she returned to England and became English tutor at St. Hugh's College, Oxford. She resigned her position in 1921 upon marrying Percy Simpson, then librarian of the English faculty library at Oxford. The couple had two children: Edward Simpson, who was killed in a mountaineering accident near Chamonix in 1953; and Mary Simpson Fleay.
Evelyn Simpson's Study of the Prose Works of John Donne was published in 1924. The first two volumes of Percy Simpson's and C. H. Herford's projected edition of the Works of Ben Jonson appeared in the following year. After Herford's death in 1931, it became clear that Simpson would be unable to finish the edition alone. In 1937, when he was 72, Evelyn put aside her work on the sermons of John Donne and joined him as junior editor for volumes 6-11, the last of which appeared in 1952.
As the Jonson edition neared completion, Evelyn undertook a comprehensive edition of John Donne's Sermons in collaboration with George R. Potter of the University of California at Berkeley; the first volume appeared in 1953. Following Potter's death in 1954, Evelyn completed the ten-volume edition alone, despite failing eyesight and her husband's increasing frailty. The final volume appeared in 1962, shortly before Percy Simpson's death at the age of 97. Evelyn then began work on an anthology of Donne's prose, but it was unfinished at her death in September 1963. Edited by her close friend Helen Gardner, with T. S. Healy, Selected Prose was published in 1967 "as chosen by Evelyn Simpson."
Scope and Contents
The Evelyn Simpson Papers document aspects of the scholarly career of Evelyn Simpson, in particular her work on a complete edition of John Donne's Sermons during the 1950s. The papers span the dates 1906-1963 and have been organized into two series: I. Correspondence and II. Writings.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Evelyn Simpson Correspondence; George R. Potter Correspondence; and Percy Simpson Correspondence. The subseries Evelyn Simpson Correspondence is further organized into Incoming Corrrespondence and Outgoing Correspondence.
Boxes 1-3 contain alphabetically arranged correspondence to Evelyn Simpson, almost entirely professional and scholarly in nature. Major correspondents include Helen Gardner, Mary Holtby, Sir Geoffrey Keynes, J. B. Leishman, James Marshall Osborn, George and Mabel Potter, and John Sparrow. Folders 76-80 hold letters from the University of California Press concerning their publication of Donne's Sermons. Outgoing Correspondence includes several folders of letters to Mary Holtby and Mabel Potter which mingle personal and professional news as well as comments on Simpson's editorial work on John Donne. The remaining two subseries contain small amounts of letters addressed to George Potter and Percy Simpson which were acquired with the Evelyn Simpson Papers.
Series II, Writings, is organized into six subseries. Sermons of John Donne, housed in boxes 5-21, contains notes, drafts, typescripts, proofs and galley proofs of the multi-volume edition of the Sermons produced by Simpson between 1953 and 1962. Box 21 also contains the subseries George R. Potter Research Materials, which includes notes by Potter, who coedited volume 1 of the Sermons with Simpson prior to his death in 1954. The subseries Other Writings Related to John Donne is housed in boxes 23-25 and includes article drafts and notes, printed copies and offprints of reviews by Simpson. Other Papers contains documentation of Simpson's research on Ben Jonson; Percy Simpson Materials includes three folders of notes and research material collected by Simpson's husband; and Other Printed Material includes offprints of reviews autographed to Simpson and a variety of newspaper and periodical clippings.
Oversize material is housed in boxes 27 and 28.
English prose literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700 -- Criticism, Textual; Learning and scholarship -- Great Britain; Scholars -- Great Britain; Women scholars; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Bald, R. C. (Robert Cecil), 1901-1965; Donne, John, 1572-1631 -- Sermons; Gardner, Helen, 1908-1986; Holtby, Mary; Keynes, Geoffrey, 1887-1982; Lewis, Mabel Potter; Potter, George Reuben, 1895-1954; Simpson, Evelyn Mary Spearing, 1885-1963; Simpson, Percy, 1865-1962; University of California Press; University of Oxford -- Intellectual life
- Correspondence, 1910-1963; Series I; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into four subseries and alphabetically arranged by correspondent within each subseries.
  - EVELYN SIMPSON CORRESPONDENCE
    - Incoming correspondence
      - Adams, Kingsley, 1954-57 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Allen, Don Cameron, 1949 Jan-May
      - Bald, R. C., 1947-63 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - Bedford, John Ian Herbert, Duke of, 1955 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Bell, Henrietta Bennet, Roger E., 1925-41
      - Benson, C. Irving, 1944 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Bradley, Henry, 1910 Feb
      - Branney, M., 1962 Aug 16
      - Brecon, Edward Swansea, 1952 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Branley, Jean, 1954 Jun 21
      - Bryson, John, 1959 Oct 24
      - Butt, J. E., 1930-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Chambers, E. K., 1933 Dec 30
      - Chapman, R. W., 1928-37
      - Churchill, Irene J., 1947 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Clark, G. N., 1959 Dec 15
      - Coffin, Charles M., 1934-49
      - Colin, H. M., 1954 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Crook, Dorothy, 1945 Jun 22
      - Crum, Margaret, 1960-61, n.d.
      - Curtis, Myra, 1946-53 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Davis, Norman, 1958-61
      - Davis, William, 1947 Jan 17
      - Donner, H. H., 1940 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Draper, W. H., 1925 Mar 24
      - Drummond-Hay, R., 1961 Jan 19
      - Durham, G., 1950 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Eccleshare, C. F., 1953 Sep 18
      - Evans, Joan, 1921-31
      - Farnham, Fern, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Farnham, Willard, 1957-62
      - Feil, J. P., 1958
      - Fieler, Frank B., 1960 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Firth, Charles H., Sir, 1924-32
      - Firth, Francis, Lady, 1918-36
      - Flasdieck, Hermann, 1947 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Fremantle, Bride, n.d.
      - Furse, Katharine, 1915 Nov 2
      - Gardner, Helen, 1948-62 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
      - Garrod, H. W., 1933-55 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Gauger, Hildegard, 1958 Sep
      - Gosse, Edmund, 1927-28
      - Greg, W. W., 1930-36, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Grierson, H. J. C., 1942-45
      - Habenicht, Rudolph, 1958 Jul 22
      - Harrowby, Dudley Ryder, Earl of, 1958 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Haviland, J. Bernard, 1958 Jun 3
      - Hayword, John, n.y. 1930-33
      - Heaton, I., n.d.
      - Holtby, Mary, 1956-59 (Box 1, Folder 22-27)
      - Henderson, Gerald W., 1934-35 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Hopkins, Gerard, 1924 Oct 17
      - Hughes, Merrit Y., 1931 Jan 21
      - Hunt, R. W., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Hutchinson, Francis, 1931 Mar, n.d.
      - Jackson, Dorothy, 1963 Feb 16
      - Jackson, William A., 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Jones-Davies, M. T., 1957-61
      - Kelly, J. N. D., 1959-61 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Keynes, Geoffrey, Sir, 1947-62 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Krueger, Robert, 1961-63 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Legouis, Pierre, 1952-54
      - Leishman, J. B., 1956-61 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Lenoir, Nicole, 1958 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Lothian, Ker, Lord, n.d.
      - MacDonald, A. J., 1954 Jul 2
      - Martin, L. C., 1959-61 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Masefield, Constance, n.d.
      - Masefield, John, n.d.
      - Matthews, W. R., 1953 Sep 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Maxwell, J. C., 1952-58
      - Merton, Wilfred, 1949 Jun 10 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Meynell, Francis, 1931-52
      - Milgate, W., 1950 Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Mueller, William R., 1958-62
      - Nicholson, Norman, 1960 Jun 2
      - Osborn, James Marshall, 1953-63 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Park, W., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Pickard-Cambridge, A. W., 1923-27
      - Porter, J. R., 1960-61
      - Potter, George R., 1946-54 (Box 2, Folder 42-49)
      - To Potter, George R., forwarded to Evelyn Simpson, 1946-54 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Potter, Mabel, 1954-59 (Box 2, Folder 51-58)
      - Potter, Mabel, 1960-63 (Box 2, Folder 59-65)
      - Quilty, George, 1946 Nov 20 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - Raleigh, William, Sir, 1919-20
      - Robbie, H. J. L., 1920 Feb 2
      - Roberts, Isabel, 1961 Nov, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Rodenmayer, Robert N., 1959 Feb 16
      - Rosie, J. A., 1958 Feb 25
      - Sandys, Cynthia, 1957 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Selincourt, Eve, n.y. Oct 9
      - Shapiro, I. A., 1932-58
      - Simpson, C. A., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Simpson, D. C., 1949 Jan
      - Sisam, Kenneth, 1925 Jan 10
      - Skinner, Margo, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Smalley, Beryl, 1958 Mar 15
      - Smith, A. J., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - Smith, H. Clifford, 1936 May 17
      - Smith, Logan Pearsall, 1921
      - Sparrow, John, 1920-58 (Box 2, Folder 72-73)
      - Spencer, Theodore, 1929-31 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - Steward, Russel, 1963 Mar 26
      - Tennyson-d'Eyncourt, Pamela Gladstone, Lady, 1927 Aug 11 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Thomas, Roger, 1946 Nov 19
      - Tuve, Rosemond, 1959 Feb 28
      - University of California Press, 1953-63 (Box 3, Folder 76-80)
      - Walker, Luke, 1926 Jan 28 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Wallet, Carlie, 1934 Jul 11
      - Williamson, Goddard, Bishop of Swansea and Brecon, 1952-53
      - Wasson, R. Gordon, 1960 Aug 29 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Watson, George, 1953 17 Oct
      - White, Elizabeth Wade, 1955-63
      - Wilson, F. P., David, Joanna, 1959-62, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Wilson, J. Powell, 1935-61
      - Woolecombe, K. J.
      - Unidentified, 1933-60 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Outgoing correspondence
      - Holtby, Mary, 1955-59 (Box 3, Folder 85-86)
      - Holtby, Mary, 1960-62 (Box 3, Folder 87-88)
      - Potter, George, 1945-54 (Box 4, Folder 89-97)
      - Potter, Mabel J., 1954-62 (Box 4, Folder 98-106)
      - Gauger, Hildegard, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - Simpson, Percy, n.y. Oct-Dec
      - Williamson, Rev. Edward, 1952 Dec 8
      - Unidentified, 1926-62 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - GEORGE R. POTTER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Fischel, Walter J., 1953 Aug 18 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - French, J. Milton, 1949-50
    - Hanford, James H., 1953 Apr-May
    - McManaway, James G., 1942, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Stephens, L. Edgar, 1953 Nov 12
    - University of California, Library, 1949 Jun 10
    - Willeford, Bill, n.y. Oct 30 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Williams, Arnold, 1951 Mar 9
    - Unidentified (7), 1948-53, n.d.
  - PERCY SIMPSON CORRESPONDENCE
    - Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature, 1954 Mar 29 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Glyn, Mills & Co., 1960 Mar 28
    - Hake, Henry M., 1923 Sep 3 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Hargreaves-Mawdesley, W. N., 1957 Jul
    - Harrison, G. B., 1932 Feb 3
    - Thompson, Francis, 1947 Jan 2 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Unidentified, 1947 May 19
    - P. Simpson to Clarendon Press, 1921 Jan 6
- Writings, 1919-1963; Series II; 9.17; (22 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is organized into subseries and each subseries arranged by type of material.
  - SERMONS OF JOHN DONNE
    - Notes and rough material
      - Volume IX, textual notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 115)
      - Volume X, Hebrew Words, textual notes, corrigenda, et al. (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - Volume X, textual notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - Volume X, textual notes, St. Augustine, Commentators and Controverialists (Box 5, Folder 118)
      - Volume X, Greek fathers, Hebrew Words, critical apparatus, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 119-122)
      - Volume X: Donne's scriptural references, knowledge of Hebrew, Greek and Latin translation (Box 5, Folder 123)
      - Volume X, misc., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 124)
      - Volume X: "English versions", scriptural checks, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 125)
      - Notes on Lothian MS, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 126-127)
      - Notes on "Folio" MS, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 128-130)
      - "Death's duell": textual noes to sermon, variants, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 131)
      - Notes on manuscripts; MS variants in sermon on Matthew 21:44 (notebook), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 132-134)
      - Notes on manuscripts; misc. variants, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 135-136)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 137-143)
    - Notebooks
      - Small alphabetized notebook, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 144)
      - Large alphabetized notebook, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 145)
      - Relations of manuscripts, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 146)
      - Dobell manuscript notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 147)
      - "Index to Introductions and Titles" (Box 7, Folder 148-151)
    - Notecards
      - Box 1 (Box 8, Folder 152)
      - Box 2 (Box 9, Folder 153)
      - Box 3 (Box 10, Folder 154)
    - Rough drafts and manuscripts
      - Volume I, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 155)
      - Volumes IV and V (Box 11, Folder 156)
      - Volume IX, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 157)
      - Volume X, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 158-160)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 161-167)
    - Typescripts by volume
      - Volumes I and II (Box 12, Folder 168)
      - Volume III, table of contents and introduction (Box 12, Folder 169)
      - Volume III: Introduction, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 170-171)
      - Volume III: Sermons, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 172)
      - Volume IV: Introduction, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 173)
      - Volume IV: Sermons, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 174-176)
      - Volumes V and VI: Introductions (Box 12, Folder 177)
      - Volume VII, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 178-181)
      - Volume VIII, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 182-184)
      - Volume IX, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 185-192)
      - Volume X: Introduction, appendices (Box 14, Folder 193-196)
      - Volume X: Sermons, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 197-201)
      - Undated/Unnumbered (Box 14, Folder 202-205)
      - Undated/Unnumbered (Box 15, Folder 206-214)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 215-218)
    - Galley proofs
      - Volume III, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 219)
      - Volume IV, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 220-222)
      - Volume V, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 223)
      - Volume IX, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 224-226)
      - Volume X, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 227-231)
    - First page proofs
      - Volume II, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 232-234)
      - Volume III, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 235-236)
      - Volume IV, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 237-238)
      - Volume V, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 239-242)
      - Volume VI, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 243)
      - Volume VIII, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 244-247)
      - Volume IX, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 248-251)
      - Volume X, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 252-255)
      - Unidentified sermon proofs, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 256-264)
      - Reviews sent to Evelyn Simpson, 1953-63 (Box 21, Folder 265-268)
      - Other reviews, 1919-53 (Box 21, Folder 269)
    - Visual materials
      - Etching: "James Hay, Earl of Carlisle", n.d. (Box 21, Folder 270)
      - Images and small photostats (Box 21, Folder 271)
      - Lothian manuscript photostats, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 272)
  - GEORGE R. POTTER MATERIALS
    - Visual materials
      - Photostats, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 273)
    - Notes
      - Textual notes on Volume V, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 274)
      - Biblical reference checks, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 275)
      - Miscellaneous variants, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 276)
      - Other notes, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 277-278)
      - Notecards, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 279)
  - OTHER WRITINGS RELATED TO JOHN DONNE
    - Notes and Manuscripts
      - Book of Common Prayer, Ignatius his Conclave, Pseudo-Martyr, "Proposed volumes of selections from Donne", n.d. (Box 23, Folder 280)
      - Devotions upon Emergent Occasions, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 281-283)
      - Devotions upon--Paradoxes and Problems (Box 23, Folder 284-288)
      - Donne as an Artist in Prose, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 289)
      - Essays in Divinity; Devotions-- Juvenalia (Box 23, Folder 290)
      - John Donne on the Psalms and Gospels (Box 23, Folder 291)
      - John Donne's Sermons on the Psalms and the Gospels (Box 23, Folder 292)
      - "John Donne on the Psalms and Gospels", "Donne and the Elizabethan Stage", typescript carbon (Box 23, Folder 293)
      - Review for R. E. S.; Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 294)
      - A Study of the Prose Works of John Donne (Box 24, Folder 295-296)
      - The Way of Peace, or Death's Destruction, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 297-298)
      - Unidentified drafts and typescripts (Box 24, Folder 299-300)
    - Publisher's Proofs
      - Donne: The Courtier's Library, 1930 Sep-Oct (Box 24, Folder 301-302)
      - Essays in Divinity, 1951 Oct 24 (Box 24, Folder 303-304)
      - "Paradoxes and Problems", "More Manuscripts of Paradoxes and Problems", "Biographical Value of Donne's Sermons" (Box 24, Folder 305)
        Also unidentified proofs relating to sermons
      - "The Prose Works of John Donne", 1948 (Box 24, Folder 306-307)
      - Various reviews by Simpson, "John Donne's Sermons on the Psalms and Gospels", 1962, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 308)
    - Final printings
      - Chronological Arrangement of Sermons; More Manuscripts of Problems and Paradoxes, 1958, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 309)
    - Notebooks
      - Donne's Books in Middle Temple, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 310)
      - Notes on Ignatius his Conclave, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 311)
      - Notes by H. J. C. Grierson, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 312)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Visual materials
      - Manuscript photostats of Jonson's "Masque of Queenes", n.d. (Box 25, Folder 313-315)
        Related Archival Materials note
        See also: Oversize, Box 27, folder 331-333
      - Other visual materials, n.d.
        See: Oversize, Box 28, folder 334-337
    - Drafts and typescripts
      - Jonson and Dickens: A study in the comic genius of London (draft and typescript), 1943, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 316)
      - Jonson's Later Plays and Masques (Box 25, Folder 317-318)
      - Sir Thomas Overbury, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 319)
      - Trollope, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 320)
    - Printed Material
      - Proofs, 1944, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 321)
        Jonson and Dickens, a Study The Masque of Queenes Unidentified (Jonson) Clipping - Jonson's "A New Year's Gift"
    - Notebooks
      - "Provençal", 1906 (Box 26, Folder 322)
  - PERCY SIMPSON MATERIALS
    - Visual materials
      - Inigo Jones, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 323)
    - Notes
      - Lecture and other notes (Box 26, Folder 324)
    - Printed Material
      - Miscellaneous printed material, 1951, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 325)
  - OTHER PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Donne-related articles, 1931-46, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 326)
    - Articles not related to Donne, 1918-59, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 327-330)
- Oversize, 3.34; (2 boxes)
  - Facsimiles of "Masque of Queenes", n.d. (Box 27, Folder 331-333)
  - Miscellaneous photostats, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 334-337)